好了 小子们
All right, boys.
我们开饭吧
Let's eat.
就快到了
Be there soon.
我一直在想
I've been thinking.
如果你没那打算的话 完全可以不用回帮会里的
If you don't want to, you don't need to go back to the collegium.
安东尼的命令现在已经无效了 不是吗？
Antony's orders don't stand now, do they?
可它也没被废除
The orders haven't been rescinded.
现在那儿什么都没了 只有小偷和杀手
There's naught there but thieves and cutthroats.
不适合孩子们生活
It's no life for children.
那该去哪儿？
Then where?
要在哪儿才能拥有身份与尊严？
Where can they find respect and dignity now?
到哪里才能不受人轻侮？
Where can they live without contempt?
带她们去哪儿都行 除了那儿
Take 'em anyplace but there.
走得远远的 谁会认出你？
Go far away. Who's to know?
你要我撒谎么？
Lie, you mean?
生活在谎言之中？
Live dishonestly?
该说谎时就得说 不对吗？
Well, there's lies and there's lies, innit?
这边走 对了 过来
This way. That's it, come on.
这儿怎么了？
What's this, then?
放到这儿来
Put it right here.
是谁给你们命令封路的？
By whose authority do you block the road?
盖乌斯·屋大维·凯撒的命令
By authority of Gaius Octavian Caesar.
勒住你的马 会轮到你的
Go hold your horse. We'll get to you.
姐姐
Sister!
还不行
Not yet.
没有钱我们还不能跑
We can't run off without any money.
屋大维把他的军队带到罗马来了？
Octavian has brought his army to Rome?
得胜之后昨天就地扎营了 有15000人呢
Put up camp yesterday on the field of Mars-15,000 men.
你那小子还真是好斗啊
Your boy's a bit aggressive, isn't he?
我那小子给了把你那大人都修理了一顿
My boy gave your man a whipping.
希望他知道自己在干什么
Expect he knows what he's doing.
我亲爱的孩子
My dear boy.
你可是共和国的英雄
You are a hero of the Republic.
就算是恺撒他本人也不会胜得这么漂亮
Caesar himself could not have conjured a finer victory.
我就是恺撒本人
I am Caesar himself...
严格来说
technically speaking.
当然
Indeed.
代表元老院
On behalf of the Senate,
我们谨致以深深的谢意
we are deeply thankful.
似乎这谢意还不足以让你们 按我的要求举办凯旋的仪式啊
Not quite thankful enough to give me the triumph I asked for?
这个嘛 我正打算帮你个忙
Now there, I'm doing you a favor.
穆提那之战确实胜得漂亮 这没话说
Mutina was a lovely victory, it's true.
不过胜利属于别的罗马人
But it was a victory over other Romans,
并非对你不敬
and with all respect,
不过希尔提乌斯和潘撒…
Hirtius and Pansa...
希尔提乌斯和潘撒已经死了
Hirtius and Pansa are dead.
愿神赐他们以安息
May the gods feed them honey.
他们是已经死了
They are dead.
可谁都知道实际指挥战斗的…
But it is well known that actual command of the battle
是他们俩
was in their hands.
战斗的宗旨是活下来
The purpose of a battle is to remain alive.
他们没做到 我做到了
They did not. I did.
是啊 可就算这样
Indeed.
这也还算不上完全的胜利
Even so, the victory is not quite complete.
马克·安东尼还活着 他手底下还有人
Mark Antony still lives. He still has men.
我们不得不派遣马可斯·莱彼得斯和两个军团北上
We have had to send Marcus Lepidus and two legions north.
莱彼得斯？这就是你的如意算盘？
Lepidus? Sending your very best, then?
我对莱彼得斯获胜有十足的信心
I have every confidence that Lepidus will succeed.
那么等他想要的时候 你可以再给他办一次凯旋庆典
Then he may have a triumph too if he wants one.
人民会对这个凯旋另有想法
The people would not look kindly on a triumph.
只要你还陈兵城下
Not with your army at the walls of the city.
恐怕是有点让人心头不快
A little unsavory, perhaps.
这个嘛 他说的有点道理
Now there, there he has a point.
真高兴你能这么说
How good of you to say so.
那我将怀着敬意接受你的忠告
I bend to your wise counsel, then.
- 不需凯旋庆典 - 我们可以找点合适的方法
- No triumph. - We shall find some fitting way
庆祝你的胜利
to celebrate your glory.
也许修个恺撒神庙好纪念胜利什么的
Perhaps a temple to Caesar victorious.
- 听起来不错吧 - 如果我不能举办凯旋庆典
- That sounds rather fine, doesn't it? - If I cannot have a triumph,
那我宁可得到执政官的位子
I was rather thinking of taking the Consul's chair.
你想当执政官？
You wish to be consul?
只不过是个虚名而已 我也知道
It's a vanity, I know.
可我认为我应该理应得到 而这也能够让我手底下的人高兴
But I think I deserve it, and it would please my men.
你才19岁啊
You're 19.
你连当元老院议员都嫌太年轻 更不用说执政官了
You're too young to be a senator, leave alone consul.
我亲爱的孩子 切勿听信谗言
My dear boy, you've been listening to bad advice.
你没政治经验 也没关系网
You have no experience. You have no connections.
可他有军队
He has an army.
这个嘛…
Well...
我会跟其它的元老院议员们谈谈
I'll speak with the other senators.
看看有没有这个可能性
We'll see if it's possible.
哪怕你就是当上了执政官
Though if you were to be consul...
你也必须保证听从我的指点
you must promise to be guided by my counsel.
这里头的关系可是错综复杂
It is an office of high complexity.
我非常清楚自己经验不足
And I am well aware of my inexperience.
我保证三缄其口 除非得到您的提点
I will not utter a word without your advice, your...
你的首肯
consent.
这样啊…
Well...
也许还是有点余地的
perhaps something can be done.
傲慢自大的犊子
Bumptious young fool.
居然要执政官的位子
The consul's chair indeed.
是啊 不过你应该让他如愿的
Yes, but you will give it to him?
为什么不满足他的虚荣心呢 他又没什么危害
Why not soothe his vanity? He can do no harm.
他穿紫袍就跟穿盔甲一样 (紫色是罗马上层贵族的服饰颜色)
He will wear the purple as he wears armor,
只不过是个装成熟的孩子罢了
like a child playing at grownups.
过来 泰罗
Come, Tyro.
我现在要出发了
I'm leaving now.
你真的不跟我一起走？
Are you sure you won't come with me?
忙着呢
Busy.
母亲
Mother.
该让他来见我
He will come to me.
先摆个姿态出来 你在道义上就有优势了
Make the first gesture and you will have the moral high ground.
是我生了那个忘恩负义的东西 他该来见我
I gave birth to the ingrate. He will come to me.
- 你在做梦 他不会来的 - 那谢谢你了 好女儿
- You're delusional. He's not coming. - Thank you, daughter.
我还真是喜欢跟你这么说说话 尤其在你不嗑药的时候
I really appreciate these little chats we have in between your drug binges.
那我走了
I'll be going, then.
要我告诉他你爱他吗？
Should I give him your love?
我该怎么跟他说？
What should I tell him?
跟他说他拿光了我们的钱 叫他还回来
Tell him that he's still got all our money and we want it back.
好的 就蓝色吧
All right, the blue.
这是亚麻布做的吗？
Does it come in linen?
吹一下 添点好运气
Blow on it for luck.
这是我从奴隶主手下救回来的女儿
These are my daughters redeemed from slavery.
大女儿做了妓女
The eldest has been prostituted,
这个男孩是我老婆跟别人生的
the boy is my wife's child by another man.
你们要尊重他们
You will treat them with respect
好好对待
and kindness.
要不然我就得找你们问问理由
Or I will know the reason why.
这里近河又通风
Gets a good breeze from the river.
我们会把这里打扫干净
We'll have it swept...
再重新粉刷
and painted.
喜欢吗？
You like it?
是的 父亲
Yes, Father.
我们所有人又一起重新开始生活了
We're all of us starting again together.
也许一开始
There will be...
会有点尴尬 这是肯定地
awkwardness at first, no doubt.
但我们是一家人 大家都会在一起生活
But we're a family and we'll be together.
理当如此
As it should be.
我们再也不会提起过去了
We will not speak of the past.
是的 父亲
Yes, Father.
吃东西还是狼吞虎咽 真不明白你怎么还长得这么瘦
Still eating like a horse, I see. I don't know how you stay so skinny.
你说什么呢
How dare you?
我不瘦 只是比较苗条
I'm not skinny. I'm slender maybe.
你才瘦呢
You're skinny.
- 风怎么没把你吹走 - 被盔甲压住了
- I wonder how you don't blow away. - My armor holds me down.
妈妈说她爱你
Mother sends her love.
- 她这么说？- 她是这么说的
- Does she? - She does.
她本来是要跟我一起来的
She would have come with me, only...
只不过她发傻气地认为你该去探望她
she has this silly idea that you should come to her.
- 那她将孤独终老 - 我了解你的感受
- She'll grow old alone, then. - I know how you feel,
不过说真的
but really and truly,
让她任性一下又何妨呢？
what would it hurt to let her have her way?
她可是你母亲
She is your mother.
奥克塔维娅 你当时也在场 你该知道她是什么样的母亲
Octavia, you were there. You know what kind of a mother she is.
上帝知道 如果我要怨恨的话理由绝不比你少
The gods know I have reason to hate as much as you do.
也许还更多
More maybe.
可这又对你有什么好处呢？
But where does that lead you?
连自己的母亲都不爱 那你还能爱谁呢？
Who can you love if not your own mother?
她指使她的情人打我
She put her lover to beating me.
你高估她了
You credit her with too much power.
她一直被安东尼捏在手心里
Antony has a hold on her.
没了他 她只不过是孤单一人 茫然失措
She's scared and lonely without him.
她犯了个错误
She made a mistake.
我本来还以为至少你会站在我这边
I should have thought you at least would be on my side.
弟弟 拜托
Brother, please!
别像这样子 没什么这边那边的
Don't be like that. There are no sides.
我爱你 她也爱你
I love you. She loves you.
你总不能背弃你的家人吧
You can't turn your back on family.
是她指使她的情人殴打我
She put her lover to beating me.
他身上还粘着她的汗
Her sweat was on him.
他们上过床了 那又怎么样？
So they had made love. So?
他们是恋人
They are lovers.
别那么一本正经好不好
Don't be so damn pious.
你让家里背了一屁股债
You'd just thrown the family into ruinous debt.
就为了这个
For this!
让你玩带兵打仗
So you can play at soldiers.
难道还要我也亲自扁你一顿吗？
I might've beat you myself!
很明显没必要再谈下去了
Clearly there's no point in further discussion, then.
好了 别生气了
Please, don't be angry.
回家吧
Come home.
回家来
我不准备先进城 除非元老院任命我为执政官
I don't intend to enter the city until the Senate has ratified me as Consul.
之后我会住进恺撒的别墅
I shall then live at Caesar's villa.
如果母亲希望来拜访的话 没人拦着她
If Mother wishes to visit me there, no one will stop her.
执政官？
Consul?
你干吗自找麻烦？
Why would you invite such trouble?
我不希望你关心这种事情
I don't expect you to concern yourself with such matters.
但是在公众场合 你跟我说话得要毕恭毕敬
But in public you will speak of me only with the utmost respect.
听懂了吗？
Is that clear?
我又不会说你坏话
I would never say anything against you.
你是我弟弟
You're my brother.
感谢你的来访 姐姐
Thank you for visiting, sister.
很快我们就会再见面的
We'll see each other again soon...
等我不那么忙的时候
when I'm less busy.
看看你都变成了什么样的混帐东西
What a stupid arse you've become!
自从你走后我们可是四面楚歌
We've been hard-pressed since you left.
时刻警惕 严阵以待
Shields up, leathers braced.
我们把自己的地盘看管得很好
We've done well to hold our ground.
希望我没做错什么
I hope I've done right by you.
你干得很好 这点我毫不怀疑
You've done well, I have no doubt.
- 谢谢夸奖 - 我们一切照旧
- Thank you. - We go on as before.
波罗排行老二 你是老三
Pullo's second, you're third.
- 老三？- 嗯
- Third? - er
你说了算 头儿
Whatever you say, chief.
但是我认为我该坐第二把交椅
But I was thinking I'd be second.
现在别来 你这女人 看不见我们在谈正事儿吗？
Not now, woman! Can't you see we're talking business?
你还要点什么吗？
Anything else you'd like?
问问孩子们要什么
See if the children want anything.
好的 老板
Will do, boss.
干了这么久的帮主了
Being captain all these long months,
这样才算公道 不是吗？
it's only justice, isn't it?
如果你要公道 伙计 你算找错地方了
If it's justice you're after, brother, you're in the wrong place.
波罗老二 你老三
Pullo is second. You are third.
等我死了 波罗也死了
I die, Pullo dies,
就轮到你上 规矩就这样
you move up. That's how it works.
我跟你赌50德拉克马金币
I'll bet you 50 golden drachmae
先死的人肯定不是我
it's not me that goes first.
卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
Lucius Vorenus.
抬起你的头来 莱蒂 我无意伤害谁
Raise your head, Lyde. I'm harmless enough.
你现在留在神殿里了？
You're in a temple now?
侍奉欧博娜女神的祭坛
The altar of blessed Orbona.
很好
Good.
- 你还好吗？- 是的
- And you're well? - I am.
孩子们…
The children...
他们都好吗？
are they all right?
他们都好得很
They're well enough.
听着
Listen.
别以为你可以带他们远走高飞
Don't think you can take them away.
他们得跟着我
They're staying with me.
莱蒂
Lyde!
我的宝贝儿 宝贝儿 宝贝儿 我的宝贝儿
My loves! My loves! My loves! My loves!
感谢伟大的女神你们回来了
Praise the great goddess, you are returned.
欧博娜女神啊 我一定会遵守我的誓言
Blessed Orbona, I will fulfill my vow.
感谢女神 感谢女神
Praise her goodness. Praise her goodness.
感谢女神
Praise her goodness.
上床吧 亲爱的
Come to bed, love.
怎么了 我的公主？
What's wrong, princess?
你哭什么？
Why are you crying?
告诉我啊
Tell me.
我猜一定是我做错了什么
It's something I've done, I expect.
你干吗把我丢给这群坏人
Why do you leave me with these bad people?
他们对你还好吧 不是吗？
They treated you all right, didn't they?
告诉我谁对你不好
Name the one that didn't treat you right
- 我会去处理的 - 不是因为这个
- and I'll see to it. - It's not the point.
你为什么丢下我去找乌瑞纳斯？
Why do you leave me here for Vorenus?
他需要我帮忙
He needed my help.
我不能就这么丢着不管 那些孩子们
I couldn't let it lie. The children.
乌瑞纳斯
Vorenus...
你爱的是他
him you love.
我 才不呢
Me, no.
不是吧
No.
爱你
You, yes.
更爱他
He more.
不爱
No.
毫无疑问
No question.
如果你们俩都掉进河里
If both of you were drowning in the river,
我肯定先救你
I'd save you first.
肯定的
No question.
你发誓？
Swear?
我发誓
I swear.
你才有他一半重？
You're half his weight.
一半？
Half?
他一半的重量
Half his weight.
没那么沉 救起来容易
Not so heavy. Easier to save.
别在意了
Never mind.
母亲
Mother.
能看见你真好
It's so good to see you.
我…
I...
我的儿子
My son.
儿子
My son...
原谅我
forgive me.
原谅我 我以前是那么邪恶而残酷
Forgive me. I've been wicked and cruel.
打我吧 杀了我
Beat me, kill me.
随你喜欢 但是求你…
Do what you want, but just please...
- 求你原谅我 - 母亲 你
- please forgive me. - Mother, please...
都怪安东尼那只臭猪把我带坏了
I spit on that pig Antony for leading me astray.
我是个可怕的妈妈 可是我能改
I've been a terrible mother, but I can change.
我也愿意改 只要你给我这个机会
And I will change if you just give me a chance.
我唯一心爱的儿子
My darling only son.
上天作证
Gods be my witness...
我后悔极了
I am so sorry.
I'm so sorry.
我原谅你
I forgive you.
噢 谢谢你
Thank you.
谢谢
看看谁来了 女儿
Look who's here, daughter.
我们亲爱的屋大维慈悲为怀 宽恕我们了
Our beloved Octavian has blessed us with his forgiveness.
欢迎回家 弟弟
Welcome home, brother.
雅努斯神 (注:掌管过去与未来 善始善终之神)
Father Janus,
我请求您驱除这些孩子…
I ask you to cleanse these children
身上的黑暗灵魂
of the dark spirits that have fouled them.
感谢您带回了我的家人
I thank you for bringing my family back to me.
我向您起誓 从今天开始
I swear to you that from this day
我将摒弃黑暗
I renounce darkness
踏上光明之路
and I will walk in the path of light.
左 右 左
Right, left, right!
莱彼得斯
Lepidus...
老朋友
My old friend.
你怎么样？
How are you?
没以前好
I've seen better days.
出去吧 小子们
Off you go, boys.
我想莱彼得斯将军是不会对我…
I don't think General Lepidus has any...
动什么坏心眼的 对吧？
ill designs on me. Do you?
照目前这种状况不会
Not under present circumstances.
来吧
Come on.
我的人叛逃到你那边去时 还真是连蹦带跳…
My men deserted to your side with amazing alacrity.
不费吹灰之力 我的军营就空了
Not a single blow struck, yet my camp is empty.
太让人惊讶了
Amazing.
是的 我真该写信 感谢西塞罗和元老院
Yes, I really must write to Cicero and the Senate.
他们真是无比地慷慨
It was remarkably generous of them to give me
让我补充了这么多新兵员
so many fresh troops.
我不得不承认自己不知道…
I confess I had no idea
你在士兵当中竟有如此的声望
how popular you are with the rank and file.
当兵都喜欢能跟他们打成一片的统帅
Soldiers like a little spit and dirt in their leaders.
可能对他们来说 你太高高在上了
You were too noble for them, perhaps.
贵族架子太大
Too aristocratic.
这倒可能是真的
That may be so.
那么
So...
现在该干吗？
what to do now?
严格来说 当然了
Strictly speaking, of course,
我该宰了你
I should kill you.
我也不希望下这种毒手
I really don't wish to be punitive.
可反过来说 我又不能放你离开
But on the other hand, I can't really let you go either.
那该怎么办呢？
So... what to do?
咋办呢？
What to do?
你是否愿意当我的副帅？
Would you be willing to act as my second in command?
我的天啊
Dear me.
你还真是大度
That's very generous of you.
我 呃…
I...
接受还是拒绝？
Yes or no?
这个 我…
Well, I...
我也没办法拒绝 对吧？
I can't really say no, can I?
当然 你不能
No, you can't.
我指天发誓 是四个奶头
I swear to you, four nipples.
觉得结婚之后如何啊 波罗？
How is married life, Pullo?
还不错 女人嘛
Well enough. Women, eh?
婚姻是种古怪的安排
It's a strange, awkward arrangement to be thrust up and...
把你强行和另一个灵魂这么绑在一起
bound against another so.
不过男人和女人天生就该如此
But it seems to be the natural state of man and woman.
- 存在就是合理的 - 毫无疑问
- It must be right and good. - No doubt.
瞧我说的
Listen to me,
真是班门弄斧啊
a lamb lecturing a lion.
计划结婚了没有？
Any plans to wed, then?
- 正在考虑 - 哦
- I'm thinking about it. - oh.
这么说乌瑞纳斯和他家人都回罗马来了？
So Vorenus and his family are back in Rome?
是的
Yes.
我的朋友请你谅解
My friend asks you to understand
他依然是宣誓效忠于北方的那个人
that he remains under loyal oath to the man up north.
- 啊 - 但是他会以城市的利益为重
- oh - But he will do what's best for the city.
他承认你才是共和国合法的掌权者
He acknowledges that you're legal custodian of the Republic
会一如既往地维持和平
and will keep the peace the same as before.
告诉你的朋友我很感谢
Tell your friend I'm grateful,
不过我听说帮会之间有点摩擦
but I hear there is a deal of violence again between the collegia.
没问题的
No trouble.
我们大概需要给某些人敲敲警钟
We may need to bang a few heads together.
- 也许吧 - 用一切必要的手段
- Maybe. - Whatever needs to be done.
安定的局势是必要的
A period of calm is essential.
我们明白 但是我的朋友不肯回答将来
We understand, but my friend won't answer for the future.
他是否会去北方重披战袍杀回来…
If him up north were to come back with full armor on...
让我们尽量往好的方面想吧
We shall hope for the best.
顺便说一句 干得不错
Well done, by the way...
所有这些
all this.
谢谢你 波罗
Thank you, Pullo.
今天真是良辰吉日
What an auspicious day.
许多人献出了他们的生命 好让我们能够再次回到这里
Many gave their lives that we might stand here once again
团结在一个奉行法制的共和国政权下
united in the government of a lawful republic.
我们也理所应当地揭开新的一页
And how fitting that we welcome this new beginning
向这位罗马历史上
by swearing in the youngest consul
最年轻的执政官宣誓效忠
in the history of Rome.
他就是盖乌斯·屋大维
Gaius Octavian...
恺撒
Caesar.
尊贵的元老院议员们
Esteemed senators...
此时此刻我并非要求你们颂扬我本人
I take this first moment before you not to glorify myself,
而是向我的父亲致敬
but to honor my father.
为了他的荣誉 我宣誓接受执政官一职
In his honor I declare that my term as Consul
并将开辟一个新的纪元
shall usher in a new era.
这新纪元会带来美德
An era of moral virtue,
与尊贵
of dignity.
我们承受过的放荡与混乱将会终结
The debauchery and chaos we have had to endure will now end.
罗马将再一次
Rome shall be again
恢复其昔日荣光
as she once was
这个自豪的共和国将再次充满贞洁的女人
a proud republic of virtuous women
和诚实的男人
and honest men.
我此刻的身份并非
I speak to you now
是一名战士
not as a soldier
或一个公民
or citizen,
而是一个满怀悲痛的儿子
but as a grieving son.
我在这重生的共和国里要做的第一件事
As my first act in this reborn republic,
为了我父亲的荣誉 我提出一份议案
and in honor of my father, I propose a motion...
宣布布鲁图斯和卡西乌斯为谋杀犯
to declare Brutus and Cassius murderers
视其为共和国公敌
and enemies of the state.
无耻之徒
Outrageous!
孩子 这不是我们约好的
My dear boy, this is not what we agreed.
的确不是 但事已至此
It is not. Nevertheless, here we are.
布鲁图斯和卡西乌斯在这里仍有拥护者
Brutus and Cassius still have many friends.
你会分裂议院 破坏共和国的统一
You will split the chamber, the unity of the Republic!
你给我退下
Step away from my chair.
我的父亲丧命于此
My father died on this floor.
就在拿里
Right there.
被连捅27刀
Stabbed 27 times. Butchered...
被所谓的"朋友"任意宰割
by men he called his friends.
谁能告诉我这不是谋杀？
Who will tell me that is not murder?
谁来告诉我的军团 如同我一样爱戴凯撒的军团
Who will tell my legions, who love Caesar as I do,
这不是蓄意谋杀？
that that is not murder?
谁还要反对这项提议？
Who will speak against the motion?
来点杨柳茶？
Some willow tea, perhaps?
更想要天仙子
Henbane, more like.
一个毛孩让我栽了跟头
I've been outmaneuvered by a child.
那就去郊外
To the country, then.
新鲜空气和睡眠可以帮你解忧
Some fresh air and sleep will do you good.
写封信
Take a letter.
致马可斯·尤尼斯·布鲁图斯和 盖乌斯·卡西乌斯·朗吉努斯
"To Marcus Junius Brutus and Gaius Cassius Longinus..."
上帝…如果屋大维知道你还和布鲁图斯有联络…
Dominus, if Octavian hears that you're in communication with Brutus...
别说话
Don't talk.
只管写下来
Write.
"向共和国的英雄们…
"Heroes of the Republic,
致敬"
"greetings..."
孩子们
Children.
父亲
Father.
你们都好吗？
Are you all well?
是的
We are.
坏了？嗯？
Broken, is it?
没关系
No problem.
No trouble.
我会修好的 嗯？
I'll fix it.
很简单
Yeah, easy mend.
我们回来后我一直都很忙
I've been very busy since we've been back,
还没时间好好团聚
we've not spent enough time together...
是不是早日选个好天气
I thought maybe sometime soon we could...
我们去野外
spend the day together.
好好聚聚？
In the country.
好吗？
Would you like that?
如果你喜欢的话
If you like.
好 很好
Good. Good.
我们要聚一聚
We'll do that.
聚一聚
我锁厨房门前 你还要点什么吗？
Want anything from the kitchen before I lock up?
不用了
No.
你回来就好
It's good to have you back.
见过真的没？
Ever seen a real one?
- 什么？- 大象
- What's that? - An elephant.
见过一些
Yes. A few.
真有传说中那么大吗？
Are they as big as they say?
体型非常庞大
They're big.
却没轮子？
No wheels, though?
没有
No.
没有轮子
No wheels.
你喜欢的话 今晚我是你的人
You can have me, if you like.
我还是走了
Or I can go.
别走
Stay.
你可以走了
You can go now.
走？
Go?
桌子上有些钱 你可以拿一半
There's some coin on the table. Take half.
操你妈的
Fuck you.
你都没看到那里有多少钱
You haven't seen how much is there yet.
我不是鸡
I'm not a whore.
不是？那你在这儿做什么？
No? Then why are you here?
我以为你喜欢我
I thought you liked me.
我猜你也喜欢我
And you like me too, I suppose?
是有那个意思
Something like that.
我们还真是天仙配 把钱拿走
What a happy couple we'd make. Take the money.
去你妈的
Fuck you.
我说了
I told you.
我不是鸡
I'm not a whore.
把钱拿走
Take the money.
米西纳斯 我要走了
Maecenas, I'm going.
- 什么？- 我想走了
- What? - I'm going.
这么快？
Already?
我累了
I'm tired.
不不不不 别走
No, no, no, no. Stay.
接下来会更精彩
It gets so much better.
我们就快成为执政官了
We are seconds to the Consul now.
这不是我们该来的地方
We should not be in such places.
少装纯洁了
Don't be so fucking pious.
做了执行官都也不能风流的话 那还有什么意义？
What's the point of being seconds to the Consul if you can't have some fun?
什么？
What?
算了 你就随意吧
Never mind. Go if you like.
我听不见
I can't hear you.
想走就走吧
Go if you like.
我会的
I'm going.
我说…
I say...
这些墙是不是在溶化？
are the walls melting?
应该没有
I don't think so.
有 真的
They are, you know.
它们在溶化
They are melting.
我们都要死了
We should all die.
奥克塔维娅？
Octavia?
尽量小声地帮她沐浴扶她上床
Have her washed and put to bed as quietly as possible.
等等
Wait.
晚上好 夫人 请原谅我的匆忙
Good evening, madam. You'll excuse me if I hurry away.
深更半夜 你和我女儿在做什么？
Exactly what are you doing with my daughter in the middle of the night?
- 他绑架了我 - 哦？
- He abducted me. - oh?
我本在享受豪华宴会 和伊俄卡斯特一起
I was at a perfectly nice party with Jocasta,
然后这无…无礼的畜牲绑架了我
and this impud... impudent brute abducted me.
还带你回母亲的身边
And brought you home to Mother.
匪夷所思的绑架
That's a strange abduction.
她之前在哪儿？
Where was she?
奥克塔维娅 你最好如实交待
Octavia, you had best tell her the truth.
你去哪儿了？
Where were you?
我在纵酒狂欢 今晚是狂欢夜
I was at an orgy, Mother. It was an orgy.
狂欢夜没开始多久
Early stages. Early stages of an orgy.
酒神典礼都还没进行
The Bacchic rituals had not yet begun.
- 愚蠢的酗酒荡妇 - 不需要…
- You stupid drunken slut. - Really, there's no need for...
都是伊俄卡斯特那婊子的错 是她让你堕落了
It's that bitch Jocasta's fault. She's the one that's led you astray.
我是在狂欢 有什么了不起？
So I was at an orgy. Who cares?
要是你弟弟发现了 他会怎么想？
What do you think your brother will do if he finds out?
我才不在乎他怎么想
I pull a hair for what my brother will do.
哦 是吗？
Oh, really?
当他在广场上对平民鼓吹虔诚和贞操时
Whilst he's at the Forum preaching piety and virtue to the plebs,
你却在狂欢宴上跟奴隶交欢
you're sucking slave cock at an orgy.
你说这成何体统？
How do you think that looks?
- 他会把你流放到边疆 - 他不会的
- He'll banish you, at the very least. - No, he won't.
我也没有和奴隶交欢
And I sucked no slave cock.
我都还没来得及去
It hadn't got to that part.
被流放 我和你…
Banished. Gone.
被驱逐到肮脏的希腊岛屿上
And me with you, to some filthy Greek island.
不许你对外张扬此事
Don't you dare say a word to anyone about this.
不 当然不会
Never. Of course.
为什么会说"当然"？
What do you mean, "Of course"?
为什么你不会跑去向你的上帝和主人告密？
Why wouldn't you run and tell your lord and master?
因为…我不会的
Because... I wouldn't.
为什么不？告诉我
Why not? Tell me.
因为…
Because...
因为我爱她
Because I love her.
你之所以这么说
You only say that
是因为你不了解我
because you don't know me.
不不 我很了解你
No. No, I know you very well.
你很善良
You are kind
充满热情
and full-hearted
又美丽动人
and beautiful.
只要你开口 我愿为你摘下天上的星星
And I would tear down the sky for you if you asked me to.
哎哟
Well...
如果你再当我的面那样辱骂她
If you ever speak to her again like that in my presence,
我会…
I shall...
我会非常生气
I shall be very angry.
- 兄弟 怎么了？- 西塞罗来信了
- Brother, what's afoot? - Letter from Cicero.
屋大维那小子逼迫元老院
The boy Octavian has forced the Senate
宣布我们为谋杀犯 共和国的公敌
to declare us murderers and enemies of the Republic.
荒谬 那是犯法的
Well, that's an outrage. That's a crime.
他这回是大错特错了
No, it's a terrible blunder.
屋大维想稳定元老院和他手下关系
Look, Octavian was set fair to unite both Senate and people behind him.
而元老院担心如此会滋生另一个暴君
Now the Senate fears they have created another tyrant.
西塞罗请求我们尽快归巢
Cicero begs us to return as soon as we can
恳求我们去拯救共和国
and begs us to save the Republic.
书吏官
Scribe!
那么屋大维只有4支军团 对不？
So Octavian has only the four legions, no?
安东尼有7支。我们胜券在握
Antony, seven. That's the beauty of it.
你想 安东尼和屋大维的矛盾
Look, Antony and Octavian hate each other
远大于和我们的冲突
far more than they hate us.
不久会为夺权而打得你死我活
Soon enough they must fight for supremacy.
我们坐取渔翁之利 扫荡其余残兵败将
We need only wait, mop up the survivors.
书吏官
Scribe!
终于等到我们出头之日了
Now this, this is what we've been waiting for.
你来了 写封信
There you are. Take a letter.
"致西塞罗…"
"To Cicero..."
- 干杯 - 干杯
- Bacchus. - Bacchus.
你终于回来了
So, you're back.
找到孩子们了？
Find your children?
- 是的 - 听说她们成了奴隶
- I did. - They were slaves, I hear.
没错
They were.
我真为你高兴 没有什么比家人更重要了
I'm happy for you. Nothing more important than family.
的确 所以我才找你们
That's true. That's why I've come to see you.
我不想孩子们过得忐忑不安 想跟你们讲和
I don't want my children to live in fear. I want us to make peace.
讲和？
Peace?
是新执政官的意思
The new Consul demands it.
- 哦 你和他谈过了？- 他和波罗是旧友
- Spoke to him, did you? - He and Pullo are old friends.
噗 你"噗"什么？
What do you mean, "bah"?
算了 兄弟。
It's all right, brother.
库塔没有不敬的意思 是不是？
Cotta here means no offense, do you, Cotta?
这样的流血冲突 对生意和城市都没好处
This bloodshed, it's bad for business, it's bad for the city.
都是因你而起
Bloodshed started by you.
我不否认 我当时的确…
I won't deny it, I was...
很愤怒 但现在我很冷静
angry, but now I'm calm.
我清楚看到我们受尽了折磨
I can see clear, I can see that we've all suffered enough.
- 你 莫密欧 你死了多少人？- 不多
- You, Memmio, how many men you lost? - A few.
嗯 你 库塔 多少？
You, Cotta, how many?
没你的多
Not as many as you.
那些死去的丈夫
All good men,
妻子和孩子意味着什么？
wives and children gone, and for what?
意味着我们助长了敌人的势力
All we've given is strength to our enemies.
只要我们三人和解
With peace amongst us three,
艾萨伯和其他帮会
Acerbo and the lower collegia
会像以前一样对我们卑躬屈膝
will have to kiss our feet as they once did.
那你开什么条件？
What terms do you suggest?
你们共享阿格希码头
Your two collegia will have the Argosy docks.
至于怎么分 你们自己决定
You can divide them between you as you wish.
- 我们要留住欧斯提安人 - 他们想和我们入伙
- We keep the Ostians. - The Ostians want to come with us.
无论如何 他们留驻艾文台山
Nevertheless, they stay with the Aventine.
不过可以先给你们点甜头…给你们
But you can have a taste. Let's say...
百分之五
five percent.
每个人
Each.
如你们所愿
If that'll make you happy.
那就讲和
Peace, then.
- 他们会以为我们没骨气 - 随他们去
- They'll think we've gone soft. - Let them.
我们需要时间巩固势力
We need time to regain our strength.
让他们为争夺阿格希闹内讧
While they're fighting over the spoils of the Argosy,
我们争取时间增强人力和整顿秩序
we'll be recruiting men and restoring order.
他变软弱了
He's gone soft.
或许是 或许不是。等着瞧吧
Maybe, maybe not. We'll see.
至于阿格希
About the Argosy, then.
我们对半分 如何？
We'll split half and half.
分个屁
Bollocks we will.
当心 快 你能行的
Careful! Come on, you can do it.
哦 孩子们
The children!
- 你们来这里做什么？- 我们逃跑了
- What are you doing here? - We've run away.
逃？为什么？
Run away? Why?
我们不要留在恶魔身边
We can't stay with that evil man.
- 孩子们 过来 - 他是你们的父亲
- Children, come along. - He is your father.
他害死了妈妈
He killed Mama.
- 诅咒我们成为奴隶过下贱的生活 - 我知道你们受不了
- He cursed us to slavery and disgrace. - I understand it's a hard thing to bear,
- 但木已成舟 - 我恨他
- but it is as it must be. - I hate him.
因为仇恨 你就带着弟妹在街上乱闯？
And for hatred you lead your brother and sister unprotected into the street?
我会照顾他们的 我们有钱
I will take care of them. We've got enough money.
手脚快的小偷立刻就能偷光这些钱
The first thief that crosses your path will have that, and then what?
然后怎么办？你们在外无依无靠 要怎么生活？
You're alone in the world. How will you live?
靠偷窃？
By stealing?
还是卖淫？
By whoring?
如果不得已的话 我会的
If I have to.
那你妹妹呢？
And your sister?
她长大了也卖淫？
When she turns woman, shall she be a whore also?
你弟弟做娈童？
Your brother a catamite?
你们能逃到什么地方？
Where will you run
会逃过乌瑞纳斯的手掌心吗？
that Vorenus will not find you?
你们是他唯一的亲人
You're all he has left.
他会追你们到天涯海角
He'll not rest until he has you back.
你们必须留在他的身边
You must stay with your father.
只要你住在他的屋檐下
And while you live under his roof
你就必须把对他的仇恨深深的藏在心中
you may carry your hatred like a stone inside you,
绝对不能让他发现
but you mustn't ever let him see it.
永远不能
Ever.
你要做个孝顺的女儿
You must be an obedient daughter.
向他下跪
Kneel to him. Tell him you love him.
- 告诉他你爱他 - 不可能 你母亲希望你们活下去
- Never. - Your mother wants you to live.
相信我 这是你唯一的机会
Believe me, this is your only chance.
他们唯一的机会
Their only chance.
你母亲还在世的话 也会这么想的
It's what your mother would have wanted.
- 他会识破我在说谎 - 不会的
- He will know I'm lying. - No.
你的爱和原谅…
Your love and forgiveness is all he wants.
就是他想得到的 他会感谢上帝对他的宽恕
He will thank the gods for redeeming him.
要来杯红酒吗？
Would you care for a glass of wine?
谢了 我不是来闲扯蛋的
Thank you, no. This is not a social call.
开门见山吧
I will not prevaricate.
作为元老院的领导者 我必须…
As leader of the Senate, I must ask...
不 我强烈要求…
Rather, I must formally demand
你交出你的军团
that you surrender command of your legions.
你现在是和罗马执政官说话
You are speaking to a consul of Rome.
要我放弃我的部队？
Give up my army? And why would I do that?
你凭什么？元老院认为你的军团
The Senate feels that you have used your legions
对他们施加了不必要的压力 他们对此有所埋怨
in a coercive manner against them. They're inclined to resent it.
那我很遗憾
I'm sorry they feel so.
但恕我直言 他们的埋怨不足为惧
But with all respect, their resentment has no teeth.
如果我不服从又会如何？
What will happen if I do not do as they say?
他们或许会向你丢草鞋
Perhaps they will throw their sandals at you.
从东部传来的消息
Word comes from the east
布鲁图斯和卡西乌斯即将返回
Brutus and Cassius are returning to us.
随行的还有…
They bring with them...
他们20支军团
20 legions.
你有多少军团呢？
How many legions do you have?
4支 是不是？
Four, is it?
我当然不清楚他们的意图
I have no notion of their intentions, of course,
但我想他们对谋杀犯
but I suspect they're displeased
和共和国公敌的罪名颇不满意
to be named murderers and enemies of the state.
他们的罪行是有目共睹的
They were named so because they are so.
不和你绕圈子了
Be that as it may,
如果你解除武装
if you were to disarm yourself,
我或许会说服布鲁图斯对你手下留情
I might persuade Brutus to treat you leniently,
鉴于你的年幼无知
on account of your youth
和涉世未深
and inexperience.
最好不要再打别的算盘了
Let us not contemplate the alternative.
你和布鲁图斯的战争将会是…
A war between you and Brutus would be short...
短暂却又血腥
and bloody...
而你却没多少胜算
and not to your advantage.
20支军团？
20 legions?
他夸大其辞了
He exaggerates the number, I expect.
10支军团就足以击溃我们
Half that number would be enough to crush the men we have.
他们还需几个月才会抵达
It will be some months before they arrive.
届时我们可以组织更多的军团
We could raise more legions in the meantime.
未受训练的新兵 与饭桶何异
Fresh men, untrained. They'd only be so many mouths to feed.
该怎么办？
So, what's to be done, then?
我不知道
I don't know.
孩子们
Hello, boys.
为何这么消沉？谁过世了？
Why so glum? Has someone died?
布鲁图斯 我亲爱的孩子
"Brutus, my dear son.
我今日听说你即将归来
"I hear today that you're returning to us.
我感谢上帝并祈祷你的胜利
"I give thanks to the gods and pray for your success.
奉上你父亲的戒指
"I enclose your father's ring
那是他的父亲留给他的
"that his father gave him.
他经常说…
"He always used to say
戒指是由先帝皇冠的黄金铸成
"it was made of gold from the crown of the last king.
令尊生前喜欢类似的传说 所以我不确定戒指的真实来源
"Your father liked a good story, so I don't know if that's true.
希望能带来好兆头
"But it is nice to think so."
[近哈勒斯波海峡 希腊分界线]
我把它交给你
"I hand it on to you
并送上我崇高的爱意
"with all love and respect."
我们等道路干燥后
We wait until the roads are dry
向南进军至阿瑞提乌姆 然后就是罗马
and then march south through Arretium and on to Rome.
此乃万全之策
That is clearly the best plan of action.
你反对吗 莱彼得斯？
You object, Lepidus?
一点也不
Not at all.
你能独辟蹊径
Sounds eminently feasible.
但或许有点操之过急
A touch aggressive, perhaps.
安东尼将军
General Antony, sir.
我不怎么喜欢你的胡子
I'm not sure about the beard.
你是怎么到这儿的？
How on earth did you manage to get here
一个人？
all alone?
哦 当然不是
I'm not alone.
母牛不可能配三头公牛
A cow can't have three balls.
我听到了 并不好笑
I hear. It's not funny.
喷香扑鼻
It smells delicious.
谢谢 父亲
Thank you, Father.
希望能合你的胃口
I hope you like it.
都是一家人 嗯？
Family.
一家人
手势含义:说谎者乞求天主宽恕
【手势含义：说谎者乞求天主宽恕】